Hello friends, Doctor prasoon here. There
is no doubt you will need a health
insurance. If you don't have one, you
should definitely take a health
insurance for yourself and for your
family. But, how will you choose the right
and the best health insurance which is
available in India?. Which health
insurance plan is the right one for you?.
In this video, I am going to tell you
some tips which most of the health
insurance companies hide from customers.
These are some tips which most people
overlook when they try to find the right
health insurance plan for themselves.
Welcome back to Dofody, Online doctor
consultation. So let's get started. The
first point that you should consider is,
The network hospitals Which the
insurance company has a tie-up with.
Instead of going behind insurance
companies and searching for the best
insurance companies, what you should be
doing is, find out the best Hospital in
your area. Select that hospital
which has the most number of specialty
doctors, which has all the specialty
departments in it, which has all the
facilities, and then ask the hospital
with which insurance company they have a
cashless claim tie-up. They will give you a
list of insurance companies with whom
they have a direct tie up and from that
list usually selecting your insurance
company. You can double-check that by
visiting the insurance company's website,
selecting your state, then your district.
You can find the list of hospitals with
which the insurance company has a tie-up.These group of hospitals with which the
insurance company have a direct tie-up, these are called as a network
hospitals, who sometimes called as
connected hospitals. The advantages of a
cashless claim is huge, particularly when
an emergency condition such as a surgery
pops up in your life. You don't have to
go run around searching for money,
arranging the money to do the surgery or
to pay off the hospital bills.Your
insurance company will be
directly paying the hospital, and you
will not have to take a single penny out
of your pocket. The second point to note
is the maximum room rent the insurance
company lays down in its insurance plan.
Most of the insurance companies have a
maximum capping of the room rent which
the customer can avail. For example, if an
insurance plan offers capping of 2500
rupees as the maximum room rent per day,
and if you are opting an air-conditioned
room a single room with a room rent of
3500 per day. Normally what we think is
that we will have to pay a difference of
1000 rupees every day for the period of
hospital admission. But, that is far from
the truth. Actually what happens is that
there is something which is called as
proportionate direction. I will explain
what a proportionate deduction is. Based
on the hospital fee structure, the
service charges, the hospital fees, the
doctors fee, the nurses fee, and everything
will be different. For the patients who
are admitted in a general ward, a shared
room and in a standard AC room and even
in a deluxe room. All these charges will
be different. So if you are thinking that
you will have to just pay a 1000 rupees
difference? you are wrong! Because in the
AC standard room that you are chosen, the
doctors fee will be higher, the nursing
fee will be higher, the service charges
will be higher, the procedure charges
will be higher, and you will have to
shell out the extra difference from your
pocket, and this difference the insurance
company is not going to cover this
difference and that is called a
proportionate deduction. So, Always keep
in mind to choose the right room. If you
already have a policy or else if you are
trying to find a new health insurance
policy for yourself, try to find out
those insurance companies which does not
restrict on the daily room rent, or go
for those companies which offers a
single standard air-conditioned room
without putting a maximum limit on the
maximum room rent that you can avail
every day. The third thing that you
should be looking for is something
called as the waiting period or the
freezing period.
Most of the insurance companies have a
waiting period of one year or two years.
That means, after taking the policy you
will not be able to make any claims
within the waiting period. Most of the
standard companies have a waiting period
of one to two years, and it will
be different for different conditions.
For example, the pregnancy charges the
delivery charges will not be covered in
the waiting period, a surgery will not be
covered in the waiting period, and all
these details will be given finally
printed in the terms and conditions
which you are obviously not going to
read completely. So, always inquire these
things before you finally make a
decision to go with a certain specific
health insurance policy. Point number
four is revealing your pre-existing
medical conditions or surgical
conditions. Now what most people tend to
do is that they hide whatever medical
conditions they had when they are taking
or filling up the form for the health
insurance policy. You should never do
this, because the health insurance
company is anyway going to find out your
previous medical history when you raise
a claim, and when they find out that you
had a previous existing medical
condition for which you are raising the
claim right now. They are going to deny it,
They are going to reject it. So
instead of keep on pressing the next
button menu filling of the online form
or when you are filling of the form
offline in a paper, always reveal your
medical conditions whether it be a high
blood pressure, diabetes, a heart
condition, a kidney problem, liver disease,
whatever that you are suffering from
that you have been diagnosed earlier.
Reveal it, write it down, and let them
know that you have these conditions.The
premium will be a bit higher. But you can
be assured that these companies are
going to settle your claim if god forbid
something bad happens to you, and when
you are trying to raise a claim at the
time of an emergency, you are policy your
claim doesn't get rejected. The next
point is choosing a insurance policy
which covers pre hospitalization as well
as post hospitalization expenses. A
standard health insurance company is
going to cover anywhere between one
month pre-hospitalization
and 90 days post-hospitalization.
Some companies even go up to 120 days of
post-hospitalization. That means all the
medical expenses all the expenses for
the purchase of medicines after
discharge, your ambulance fees, all the
tests you've done before you got
admitted in the hospital, all these
things are going to be covered under
these policies. So make sure that you
choose a health insurance policy which
covers at least one month pre
hospitalization and 90 days post
hospitalization expenses. If you don't
have a cashless claim, you should also
keep in mind to keep all the bills
reports the doctor's prescription
everything in original and duplicate and
you should apply for the claim within
one month of discharge. Next point is
something related to third party
administrators. Now there are some
insurance companies which do not have a
claim settlement team of their own. So
what they do is that they depend on
certain other companies which are called
as third party administrators to inquire
into the claim.
Now these third party
administrators goes into the hospital checks whether the patient has got
admitted or not ,what all tests has been
done, what are the procedures the patient
has underwent. Now that's the job of
these third party administrators. Now the
problem with third party administrators
is that they act as a link between
yourself, your Hospital, and your
insurance company. So if you are raising
a cashless claim, it is going to be
delayed When a third party administrator
has got involved. Your discharge will be
getting delayed. You will have to shell
out some money from your pocket and the
overall experience is not going to be so
good when compared to another health
insurance company which has its own
claim settlement team. Now this has
happened to me when my father got
admitted for an angioplasty procedure.
Our hospital stay was not a pleasant one,
there was a third party administrator
involved in our case, and the discharge
process got delayed. Even though we had a
cashless claim the whole process got
delayed because of the involvement of
the third party administrator. So what I
recommend is that you should always go
with a health insurance company which
has its own or in-house claim settlement
team. Now there
are some other special plans
such as the cancer care plan and there
are other topper plans, super topper
plans, which you can get in addition to
the policies that you're holding. The
topper plans and the superb topper plans
will cover the amount in extra of what
the sum assured you have been guaranteed.
If you have hospital expenses in any
process the amount which your policy has
assured then the super topper plans was
going to help you out. The super topper
plans will also come at a low premium. So
you should always consider buying a
super topper plan if you're some assured
is on the lower side below two lakhs or
below three lakhs, and you should always
go for special plans such as cancer care
plans if someone in your family has
already been diagnosed with cancer, if
you are at a higher risk of developing a
cancer in the future. Now another miss
concept which most people think is that,
if you disclose about the insurance at
the time of admission, the doctors are
going to over treat you they are going
to do unwanted procedures, unwanted
surgeries and all. Now this is actually a
misunderstanding, because all the
insurance companies have their own team
of medical doctors and these doctors are
going to check in with your treating
doctor whether the procedure was
actually required or not, whether the
diagnostic test your doctor has written
was actually required or not, and for
that reason the doctor who is treating
you will be on the cautious side he is
not going to write unwanted tests or do
any unwanted procedures. So, this is
actually a convenience. You can actually
have a peace of mind because of the fact
that you don't have to spend any money
when it comes to a hospital and
admission, when it comes to an emergency
hospital procedure, or a surgery. So if
you haven't subscribed to a health
insurance policy, please do it right now.
It is an absolute necessary in this age
and if you already have a health
insurance policy please let me know
which insurance policy you are using
whether you are raised any claims and
how was your experience after raising an
insurance claim. So I hope you really
liked this video, if you haven't
subscribe to our Channel,
please subscribe right now and when you
do that, please click on the bell icon, so
that you don't miss out on any of our
future videos. I will talk to you guys in
the next video. Until then it is me Doctor.
prasoon signing off. Take care, stay healthy
and thank you so much for watching.